字幕來源: Raining.in.the.Mountain.1979.D9.MinisD-TLF
修正校訂: 非傲慢即偏見@SubHD
A Lo & Hu Co-Production
羅胡聯制有限公司  出品
RAINING IN THE MOUNTAIN
片名: 空 山 靈 雨
Presented by King HU, WU Sau-yee
出品人: 胡金銓  胡樹儒
Executive Producers LO Kai-Muk, CHUNG Ling
監製: 羅開睦  鍾玲
Starring HSU Feng as White Fox,
主演: 徐楓 飾 白狐
SUN Yueh as Esquire Wen, TUNG Lin as Chiu Ming,
孫越 飾 文安   佟林 飾 邱明
WU Chia-hsiang as Master Wu Wai,
吳家驤 飾 悟外法師
WU Ming-tsai as Gold Lock, LU Chun as Hui Wen
吳明才 飾 金鎖   魯純 飾 慧文
Guest Starring SHIH Chun as Hui Tung
客串: 石雋 飾 慧通
Art Director King HU
美術: 胡金銓
Martial Arts Director WU Ming-tsai
武術指導: 吳明才
Edited by King HU
剪輯: 胡金銓  蕭南
Cinematography Henry CHAN
攝影: 陳俊傑
Music by NG Tai Kong
音樂: 吳大江
Assistant Directors TUNG Lin, Fred TAN Han-Chung
副導: 佟林  但漢章
Produced by HON Kap-Chan
製片: 韓甲振  陳嘉雯
Written and Directed by King HU
編導: 胡金銓
Three Treasures Temple is just beyond that shrine.
過了那座小廟  才是三寶寺的地界
See that senior monk?
你看到那位大和尚了嗎
He's the temple guardian.
他就是護廟的韋陀
As long as he's on duty,
有他守在這兒
outsiders dare not set foot here.
閒雜人等休想越雷池半步
Brother.
師傅
Please follow me.
請這邊走  我帶路
Who is he?
誰
Brother Hui Ssu.
慧思師傅
Welcome!
三位施主
This is my concubine.
這是小妾
Madame.
如夫人
Esquire Wen,
文居士
the Abbot sent me to welcome you.
師父特地派貧僧來恭迎三位施主
Thank you!
不敢當
When I received the Abbot's letter
我一接到老禪師的信
I rushed right over.
馬上就趕來了
How is the old master?
他老人家的身子怎麼樣了
Not well.
不太好
He had a fainting spell two days ago,
前天痰上來了  一度昏迷不醒
but he's a little better today.
今天好了點兒
I'm afraid his time is not long.
大概離西遊之際不遠了
This is the famous Three Treasures Temple.
這就是天下聞名的三寶寺
What are the "three treasures"?
這廟裡有哪三件寶物啊
Not worldly but spiritual treasures:
這三寶不是世俗所說的寶物
the Buddha, the Dharma and the monastic community.
是佛家所謂的佛  法  僧
I don't understand.
我不懂那些個
Do you mean Tripitaka's...?
你說的那個什麼玄
The Mahayana Sutra in Tripitaka's own hand.
玄奘法師手抄的《大乘起信論》殘卷
How much is it worth?
那值多少錢吶
It's priceless.
無價之寶
I've brought aged ginseng from the north.
我帶來了一些關東老山參
Perhaps it can help the Abbot.
也許有點兒用處
Many thanks!
盡人事吧
The Abbot told me to inform you
師父叫貧僧帶口信給居士
that before he dies,
他老人家想在西遊之前
he must name a successor.
選出一位新住持
Because we've so many worthy monks,
因為三寶寺廟大人多
he's asked lay friends to assist him.
就請了幾位方外的朋友  來商量商量
Who else has he invited?
除了我之外  還請了些什麼人
I don't know.
這就不清楚了
The Abbot also thanks you
師父叫貧僧特地向居士致意
for all the donations
這幾年
you've given us over the years
居士佈施三寶寺不下十萬兩銀子
and your warm support.
又處處照應廟裡的和尚
Don't mention it.
這點兒小意思  不要提了
The Abbot has another request.
師父還有個請求
- Does the temple need more...? - No, we're financially sound.
- 是不是還要  - 不不不  廟裡能維特
He asks you
師父請求居士
to lend your support to the new abbot.
對將來選出的新住持多多照應
But of course.
一定一定
Brother Hui Ssu.
慧思師傅
Who do you expect him to choose?
依你看  老禪師想傳衣缽給誰呢
It's not for me to speculate.
傳法大事  貧僧不敢妄加揣測
- Let them take your luggage. - Yes, sir!
- 管家  把東西交給他們  - 是
- Take the valet to his room. - Yes, sir!
- 帶管家到廂房  - 是
This way.
請
Your meal will be served shortly.
兩位歇一會兒  齋飯馬上就送來
Thank you. You're dismissed.
好  你去忙吧  不要招呼了
Let's eat.
吃飯吶
Go ahead. I'll just be a minute.
你先吃  我就來
Hurry!
走
Up there!
上去
There it is!
是這兒
Come on!
走
Hurry!
( No Admittance )
( 僧俗止步 )
It must be here somewhere. Keep watch!
大概是這兒  你給我看著點兒
OK.
好
Find it?
怎麼樣
No!
沒有啊
What does it look like?
那本經是什麼樣的
It's a long scroll.
聽說是個長手卷
Wait...
你等一等
The door's unlocked.
那門好像沒鎖上啊
Unlocked? It can't be.
門沒鎖上  不會吧
Let's take a look.
咱們過去看看去
- Look! - It's open!
- 你看  - 沒鎖啊
- Hurry, tell Brother Hui Wen. - OK.
- 快去告訴二師哥吧  - 噢
Brother Hui Wen!
二師哥
What is it?
什麼事
The Scripture Hall door is unlocked.
那個藏經樓的門沒鎖
Yes, I opened it.
噢  是我開的
- Then left it unlocked? - Yes.
- 那就不用鎖了  - 唉
What'd he say?
怎麼樣
He said to leave it open.
二師哥說不用鎖了
This way.
走這邊
Was it a trying journey?
您這一路上辛苦了
Not so bad.
哪裡
Good day.
二位施主
Take the luggage to the guest rooms.
扛到客房去
Madame!
施主
Over there!
那邊
What is it?
怎麼
Strange!
奇怪
Brother Hui Tung, who is that?
慧通師傅  這是誰
Esquire Wen's new concubine.
文安新娶的如夫人
Esquire Wen?
文安
The wealthy landowner from Chiang Tung?
就是那個江東的那個大財主
I know him.
我認識他
Unbelievable!
想不到
You know the woman?
你認識這個女人
Yes.
認識
Who is she?
誰
She's called White Fox. A thief.
女飛賊白狐
A thief? Are you sure?
女飛賊  不會吧
It's her.
是她
Did you see it, General?
將軍  您瞧見沒有
She has a master key.
她身上還帶著百合鎖
Oh? I didn't notice.
這我倒沒留神
I arrested her once in the north,
我在關外當差的時候抓過她
but she escaped.
押在半路  她跑了
I don't know Esquire Wen very well,
我和文安雖然是泛泛之交
but I should inform him
可是他娶了一個女飛賊
that he has married a thief.
我應該告訴他一聲
Brother Hui Tung, please arrange a meeting.
慧通師傅  你去約一約文安
Very well!
好
General, wait!
等一等  將軍
What is it?
怎麼
There's more to this than meets the eye.
這裡邊大概另有文章
You were too careless.
你也太沉不住氣了
You brought me here
我來這鬼地方
to steal that damn scroll for you.
就是為了給你偷那本破書
So what was I supposed to do?
要不然我來幹什麼
Wait for the right time!
那你得慢慢來呀
This temple food is awful!
這麼大個廟  吃這種玩意兒
Everyone here eats the same food.
連廟裡的人都吃這個
Those leading spiritual lives for ego luxuries.
修行的人不能講究享樂
I'm not leading a spiritual life!
我又不修行
Given your history,
你從小就不幹好事
perhaps you should!
實在應該修行修行
Nonsense!
你少扯閒片兒
I don't understand...
我就不明白
With your wealth you can buy anything.
你家財萬貫  要什麼有什麼
What do you want with a ragged old scroll?
還要那本破書幹什麼
What do you know?
你懂什麼
It's the Mahayana Sutra,
這是當年大唐玄奘法師
hand-copied by the great monk Tripitaka.
親手抄的《大乘起信論》
It's priceless.
是無價之寶
Money can't buy it.
多少錢也買不到
What good is it?
又不能當飯吃
It's one of a kind.
這本卷子  普天下就這麼一份
I've long dreamed of possessing it.
我想了好幾年了
I'll get it for you as soon as I can
好  我盡快把經給你弄到手
and then get the hell out of here.
早點兒離開這個鬼地方
I'm telling you,
我老實告訴你
I don't want to hang around this dump!
我不願意在這兒耗著
Don't be rash. I've got a plan.
你可別胡來  我有一定的步驟
Forget it! I'm getting out of here!
我可沒有這個耐心玩
I'll give you your money back.
這樣吧  我把錢退給你
Hire someone else. I quit.
我先走  你另請高明
Why are you so angry?
你何必這麼大火呢
I don't like waiting around!
本來嘛  我就不喜歡拖拖拉拉的
OK, OK!
好了  好了  快吃飯吧
Hey! Keep your hands off!
你幹什麼你
You paid me to steal the scroll
我告訴你  你有錢  我給你偷書
and that's all you'll get!
少來別的
So now you're a lady of virtue, eh?
你可真是三貞九烈啊
Shut up!
你少廢話
We had an understanding, didn't we?
咱可是有言在先
I sell my skills, not my body!
我是賣藝不賣身
I'm not a whore!
可不能老尺加一啊
Keep it down, will you?
你小聲點兒行不行
- Why should I? - Please, my lady.
- 怕什麼  - 姑奶奶
Who is it?
誰呀
It's me.
是貧僧
Brother Hui Wen.
慧文師傅
Greetings.
施主
Come, I'll introduce you.
我給你引薦引薦
This is Brother Hui Wen.
這位是慧文師傅
We've already met... at the Scripture Hall.
剛才在藏經樓  已見過如夫人了
Fortunately, he's our friend.
還好  慧文師傅是自己人
He's the Abbot's number two disciple
現在是智嚴老住持的二弟子
and will very likely be the next abbot.
將來是三寶寺的新住持
We can't be certain of that!
可千萬不要這麼說
Don't worry.
你放心好了
My words carry weight with the Abbot.
我的話在老住持面前  多少有點份量
I'll leave you two to your business.
你們二位談公事  我失陪了
Fine.
好
Your support is invaluable.
施主的話自然是一言九鼎了
Did you get my letter?
貧僧的信  您收到了嗎
Yes.
收到了
I can almost guarantee you the position.
十成的把握不敢說  七八成總有
Did you receive my letter?
我的信  你也收到了吧
Yes.
收到了
If I become the new abbot,
萬一貧僧要是接了衣缽
the scroll is yours!
那本卷子一定奉上
Then it's a deal!
好  咱們一言為定
We businessmen place trust above all.
我們做生意的人  講究的就是信用
I'll speak to the Abbot in a bit.
等一會兒我到老住持那兒
I'll sound him out for you.
給你探探口氣
Please, don't be hasty.
也不能操之過急
General Wang is pressing Hui Tung's case!
王將軍大力推薦師哥啊
Wang's a soldier, not a scholar.
王驥是武人
The Abbot won't necessarily heed his counsel.
老住持不一定聽他的
Let's hope not.
但願如此
I must be going.
我告辭了
OK.
好
One more thing:
還有
your concubine may move freely about,
如夫人到處逛逛  倒是無所謂
but she mustn't arouse suspicion.
就是要不著痕跡
Someone's outside.
有人
Gold Lock!
金鎖
Over here!
過來
Let him go.
不要追了
Yes.
是
Who is he?
這是誰呀
He's the famous Master Wu Wai.
這就是天下聞名的悟外法師
What is he known for?
他是幹什麼的
He's a devoted lay Buddhist.
他是維摩詰一類的人
I don't get it.
我不懂
Although he's a layman, he knows
他雖沒出家  可是精通佛法
the sutras better than most monks do!
道行比一般和尚都高啊
Then what's he doing with all those women?
他信佛  怎麼還帶一大堆女人
He's immune to sensual pleasures.
到他這境界  已經心中無色了
Him? He looks like an old lecher.
我才不相信呢  我看他是個老色迷呀
Nonsense! Even the emperor defers to him.
別胡說  當今皇上都要讓他三分
Halt!
放
It's so good you've come!
你來了  好極了
Your Reverence!
老禪師
Arise, arise!
起來  快起來
Get up!
起身
Esquire Wen.
文公子
General Wang, it's been a while.
王將軍  久違了
Over a year since we last met.
總有一年多沒見了
Master Wu Wai travels in style, doesn't he?
這位悟外法師的氣派  可真不小
I believe he too has come here
我看悟外法師
for the succession.
大概也是為傳衣缽而來
Perhaps.
也許
Who do you think will be chosen?
你看這衣缽應該傳給誰
Who do you think?
將軍看呢
Brother Hui Tung, without a doubt.
我看是非慧通師傅莫屬
Brother Hui Tung is very clever.
慧通師傅確實很有謀略
Over here.
你過來
Give it to me.
交給我
This food is for Master Wu Wai.
這是悟外居士的葷菜
I know. Now give it to me!
我知道  你交給我吧
Go on!
你去吧
Who will Your Reverence pick?
老禪師心目中是什麼人
My mind is unsteady these days
這些日子心神不定
and my old body is failing me.
大概這個臭皮囊不頂事了
That is why I seek your advice.
所以才急著找你來商量商量
The temple is a huge responsibility.
主持這麼大的廟不容易
If I choose unwisely,
如果選錯了人
disputes will arise.
將來必起爭端
General Wang and Esquire Wen have also come.
這趟我還請了王驥和文安來了
If there is a disagreement,
萬一將來起爭端
they can arbitrate.
他們也好出頭說幾句話
What are your criteria for choosing the new abbot?
那麼在人選方面  是否有個範圍
I have none.
沒有
It doesn't matter...
我想了好幾天了
...whether he is a monk or a layman,
不論是僧是俗
so long as he is enlightened.
只要有慧根就能傳法度人
Hui Ssu,
慧思
go and fetch Master Wu Wai's meal.
你去把法師的葷菜拿來
Will do.
是
Brother Hui Tung.
師哥
I'm delivering Master Wu Wai's meal.
我正要給法師拿葷菜
I'll take it. You prepare a pot of tea.
我送進去  你去沏茶
OK.
是
Your Reverence, when are you planning to choose a successor?
那麼老禪師準備什麼時候傳衣缽呢
In a few days.
就這幾天
But there's a worldly matter to attend to first.
不過我還有點兒俗事未了
A convict has purchased a permit to become a monk here.
有個流犯買了度牒  在這裡出家
Let's take a rest.
歇會吧
Nobody's around. I'll take it off.
這兒沒人  卸了吧
Thank you, officer!
謝謝你  老大爺
Not at all.
謝什麼
We've been through a lot together.
咱們相聚一場  就是有緣呢
- Is this Chiu Ming? - Yes.
- 這是邱明吧  - 是
Here's the document you need.
這是三寶寺的文書
May I see the Abbot?
智嚴師傅在不在
The Abbot sent me to take charge of him.
師父交代過  你把人交給我就行了
Make good use of your time here, friend.
好吧兄弟  你就在廟裡好好修行
Perhaps we'll meet again.
咱們再見了
Officer!
老大爺
I don't know how to thank you!
我也沒什麼話好說了
Please don't. Get up!
起來  不要這樣
Kneel.
跪下
This is the Abbot and this is Master Wu Wai.
這位是師父  那位是悟外法師
I bow to you, Reverence.
弟子邱明  參見師父
Who is your master?
誰是你師父
You are my master.
你就是我師父
Do you sincerely wish to become a monk?
你是來出家的  還是來避禍的
I do.
出家
You are a convicted criminal.
你是充軍發配的流犯
What are you charged with?
犯的什麼罪
Theft.
盜竊
So you did transgress.
你犯了偷戒
No. I was falsely accused.
弟子沒犯戒  被人陷害
By whom?
誰陷害
Lieutenant Chang Cheng.
指揮張誠
How did that happen?
張誠怎麼陷害你
My brother was a woodblock printer.
家兄是書館刻工
Our family owned a rare edition of the Diamond Sutra.
家裡藏著一部咸通版的《金剛經》
Chang Cheng wanted to buy it.
張誠想買
My brother wouldn't sell it.
家兄不肯
So Chang Cheng accused us of theft.
張誠就羅織以偷竊罪
Arise.
你起來
And then?
後來呢
He beat my brother to death in court
當堂用非刑打死家兄
and I was sentenced to serve in the army.
弟子叛了個充軍
Have you ever met Chang Cheng?
你見過張誠嗎
No.
沒有
If you happened to meet him, what would you do?
如果你見了他  你怎麼辦
Nothing.
不怎麼辦
You bear no grudge?
你不怨
Start by mopping the temple floor.
你先把這廟裡的地洗乾淨吧
Go and get the goods.
去叫人來抬貨啊
Hurry! Give it over!
快點兒  遞過來啊
Calm down.
別急  別急
Be careful!
小心點兒
Hey! Where's the money?
唉  錢呢
- Not enough! - It's plenty.
- 這多少錢吶  - 不少了
I'm taking a loss...
兩吊半吶  這不夠本兒啊
Seven strings of 100...
七吊  一百
Six strings of 320...
六吊  三百二
Six strings of 910...
六吊  九百一
Seven strings of 460...
七吊  四百六
Four strings of 650.
四吊  六百五
Stop!
停
Wrong again!
你怎麼又錯了
You! Do it over!
就你一個人  再算一遍
Esquire Wen.
文兄
General Wang.
王將軍
I just saw something strange.
文兄  我剛才看見一件怪事
While Wu Wai was preaching, his attendants
悟外法師講經的時候
were bathing in full view of the monks!
居然讓侍女當著和尚的面洗澡
Where?
在哪裡
Just over the hill.
就在後山
This way of propagating Buddhism
這種弘揚佛法的辦法
is really something new.
倒是別開生面
Going a bit far, wouldn't you say?
這有點兒太過份了吧
Very profound.
玄妙之至
I think I'll have a look.
我倒真想去開開眼界
They're still there. Follow me.
他們還沒散  我帶你去啊
OK.
好
Please.
請
What sect is it?
這算哪宗啊
No idea...
不大清楚
Gentlemen, the Abbot...
兩位施主
will see you now.
師父有請
Very well.
好  好
This way.
這邊兒請
- Please. - Please.
- 請  - 請
Please follow me.
請跟我來
Please.
請
- Gentlemen. - Your Reverence.
- 二位施主  - 老禪師
The Abbot had matters to attend to
師父說  昨天俗務纏身
and couldn't see you earlier. Apologies.
沒機會向二位請教  很抱歉
He hopes you're comfortable here.
師父還問  你們二位還住得舒服吧
Very much so!
很好  很好
The Abbot says, when his successor takes over,
師父說  將來新住持揭了示
if there's a dispute,
萬一起了什麼爭執
he'd like you two to mediate.
請二位說句公道話
Rest assured, Reverence.
老禪師  您放心
We'll do as you wish.
一定遵命
Very well.
那就好
Your Reverence,
老禪師
which of the monks
不知道老禪師
will you choose as your successor?
預備傳衣缽給哪位師傅啊
Each of them is worthy,
他們個個是佛
each is perfect in his own way.
就像水銀洩地  粒粒成圓
You two have done much for me over the years.
二位施主這些年來  幫了我不少忙
How can I repay you?
我有什麼地方能為二位效勞呢
I've heard Tripitaka's handwritten Mahayana Sutra is kept here.
久聞貴寶剎裡藏著一部玄奘法師手抄的《大乘起信論》
Would it be possible to see it?
不知道能不能瞻仰瞻仰
By all means.
這個好辦
Is Esquire Wen also interested?
文施主也有興致嗎
I've long yearned to see the treasured scroll.
早就想見識見識這個曠世之寶
Ha! It's no treasure,
什麼寶物
just a roll of tattered paper.
不過是一堆爛紙
It truly is a priceless treasure.
真不愧是無價之寶
Incomparable!
嘆為觀止
Its true value lies in its meaning.
這卷子的用處是它的文意
But of course!
當然  當然
Brother Hui Ssu, lead the way.
慧思師傅  帶路吧
Let's go!
走
- Hey, what's that? - Indeed.
- 什麼東西啊  - 是啊
- Let's go and check it out. - Sure.
- 上去看一看  - 好
Wait a second.
大家等一下
What is it?
什麼事嘛
- Let's take a look. - At what?
- 快跟我上來看一看  - 看什麼
The ground's covered with them...
怎麼弄得一地都是啊
Careful!
大家小心一點兒啊
They look like prayer beads.
這大概是念珠吧
They're unstrung!
念珠散了
Hurry!
快來
Come on, pick them up!
來來來  大家幫忙撿一下  快點兒
Give them to him.
把撿起來的念珠交給他
Here's one...
這兒還有
- Keep looking. - OK.
- 四處再找一找  - 好
There's more here.
這兒還有
Go and look by the back door.
你到後門口去看看
- Are there some more? - No.
- 還有沒有  - 沒有了
- There are some here. - Gather them.
- 這兒還有  - 拿過來啊
- They're gone. - Go look.
- 不見了  - 找找
Any more?
還有沒有啦
Here's one more!
這兒還有了
You! Who are you?
你  你是什麼人
Chiu Ming.
邱明
Chiu Ming?
What did you do before you came here?
你以前是幹什麼的
I was sentenced to serve in the army
充軍發配的流犯
but I bought a permit to become a monk instead.
現在買了度牒  出家當和尚
Since you're a monk now,
你既然依皈佛門
what are you doing with these women?
為什麼還要跟女人鬼混
Watch what you say, sir.
施主  說話請慎重點
Outrageous!
混帳
You dare lecture me?
你敢教訓我
This is preposterous!
真是豈有此理
Let's go! Don't be nosy.
快走吧  別管這件事了
Hurry! Go!
快走  走吧
What are you doing?
你幹嘛
The hook!
爪
All for a raggedy scroll...
為了那張殘卷
Sit.
坐下
Chiu Ming, tell no one about this,
邱明  這件事不要聲張
or it will be trouble for you.
傳出去  對你不利
Understood.
是
The man who struck you was Chang Cheng.
那個打你的人就是指揮張誠
Don't be afraid.
你也不用怕
Kneel.
跪下
Henceforth, you shall guard the Scripture Hall.
日後這藏經閣就歸你管
The responsibility is too great for me.
這  弟子恐怕擔不了這麼大的責任
Why is that?
你倒說說看
I've heard
弟子聽說
Tripitaka's handwritten Mahayana Sutra is kept there.
藏經樓放著玄奘法師手抄的經卷
If something should happen to it...
萬一出了事
That is a worldly view.
這都是世俗之見
The old scroll has no real value.
那幾張破紙沒什麼了不起
Brother.
師弟
Take this ginseng to Master Wu Wai.
你把這人參送給悟外法師
Tell him it's a gift from Esquire Wen.
就說是文安居士送的
Yes.
是
Brother Hui Ssu,
師弟  師弟
I'd like a word with you.
我有話跟你說
When did he take the vows?
他什麼時候剃度的
This morning.
今天早上
Why were you two in the Scripture Hall?
你們上藏經樓幹什麼
The Abbot appointed him guardian of the Scripture Hall.
師父吩咐  以後藏經樓歸他管
A convict guarding the scriptures...
叫那個流犯管藏經樓
What's the deeper meaning of this?
這又是什麼禪機
Perhaps Master will choose Hui Ssu.
我看師父也許會傳衣缽給三師弟
No, he won't!
不會  不會
Hui Ssu is too young.
慧思太年輕
You've managed the temple's assets for many years.
再說這麼多年  廟產都是由你管
No one is better suited than you.
別人來  這法輪他推不轉啊
Please don't say that!
可千萬別這麼說
If Hui Tung should overhear,
這話要是叫大師哥聽見了
there'd be no end of trouble.
可不得了啊
You're both talking rubbish!
你們說的都是廢話
Don't be foolhardy!
你可不能太冒失
My way is better.
還是我的辦法好
Listen... wait...!
我跟你說
Sir!
施主
Sir, wait!
施主  請留步
Let us begin.
我們現在來了
Your Reverence!
老禪師
I am your devoted lay friend,
我不但是您老人家方外的好朋友
but I'm also governor of this district.
也是這裡的地方官
There is a matter we must get to the bottom of.
這件事情我們非弄個水落石出不可
Feel free to speak.
施主有話請儘管說
Are you aware
這個人的出身
of this man's background?
您老人家知道不知道
Please go on.
那你說說看
He's a criminal.
這個人原是鄉間無賴
A thief!
偷了東西
He was arrested and sentenced to the army.
被抓到官廳裡  叛了個充軍
I don't know how he got the money
不知道哪裡弄來的錢
to buy his way out.
買度牒贖了罪
His Reverence is aware of this.
這些師父都知道
It was the Abbot himself who administered the vows.
是師父親自給他剃度的
Your Reverence has led a spiritual life,
老禪師  您在這裡多年靜修
indifferent to worldly affairs.
不問世俗間的事情
Do you question my judgment?
你說我失查
No, no! All I'm saying is
不  我是說
you may be unaware of his background.
您老人家對他的身世也許不清楚
But let's not dwell on that.
先不管這些
If he'd reformed, I'd let it go.
他要是能痛改前非  也就罷了
But he's up to his old tricks!
可是  他賊性難改
Oh? How has he erred?
他有什麼不規矩的舉動
He was stealing in the Scripture Hall.
就是剛才  他到藏經樓去偷東西
Luckily, Chang Cheng was on hand to stop him.
幸虧張誠看見了  他才沒能得手
It's a lie!
他瞎說
Your Reverence...
老禪師
I have reported the incident to the Abbot.
剛才的事  貧僧已經回稟過師父了
General Wang.
王將軍
May I question Lieutenant Chang?
我可不可以問張指揮幾句話
Of course.
請
Lieutenant Chang.
張指揮
How do you know he was stealing?
你怎麼知道他是去偷東西的
As it happens,
是這樣的
I saw him sneak into the Scripture Hall.
他鬼鬼祟祟地溜進藏經樓
I grew suspicious and followed him.
我就起了疑心跟進去
When I asked him what he was doing,
我問他到這兒來幹什麼
he couldn't give me a straight answer.
他支支吾吾的答不出來
Then I knew he was up to something.
我馬上就猜到了  他圖謀不軌
You guessed, Lieutenant?
張指揮是猜到的
Lt. Chang is an officer of the law.
張指揮是提刑出身
He's familiar with the likes of Chiu Ming.
對這類人最清楚了
Wasn't Lt. Chang himself an outlaw
聽說張指揮在投效朝廷之前
before he joined the constabulary?
也在江湖上混過
Let's not digress.
先不要談這些題外的話
Chiu Ming was stealing
邱明由藏經樓偷了東西出來
and Lt. Chang confronted him.
張誠問了他幾句
In shame and anger,
不料他惱羞成怒
he threw Lt. Chang from the Scripture Hall!
還把張誠從樓上打了下來
Chiu Ming! Is it true?
邱明  有沒有這回事
Yes.
有
General Wang,
王將軍
I've heard that Lt. Chang is a martial artist.
聽說張指揮的武功造詣很高啊
Indeed he is!
相當不錯
Then how is it that he was thrown down the stairs?
那怎麼會讓他從樓上打下來呢
No, no, no! This is a sacred place!
不不不不  這裡是佛門淨地
I would never violate its sanctity by fighting.
我怎麼能夠跟他動武呢
Lt. Chang would've arrested him anywhere else.
要是在外邊兒  張誠立刻就抓他歸案
But the temple
可是  現在是在廟裡
is under the Abbot's jurisdiction.
就請老禪師處理吧
Hui Tung,
慧通
what do you think should be done?
你看應該怎麼辦
According to the rules,
依照廟規
he should be expelled for thievery.
他犯了偷戒  應該逐出門牆
He assaulted an officer of the law
他打了朝廷官吏
and should be remanded to General Wang.
按照國法  應該把他交王將軍處置
Hui Wen, what do you think?
慧文  你說說看
The Scripture Hall has long been my responsibility.
藏經樓一直是由弟子管
If Chiu Ming trespassed there,
邱明居然能進去  這是弟子失職
I am at fault.
弟子應該負責
But I don't understand how it was
不過  弟子不明白
that Lieutenant Chang happened to be there.
張指揮到藏經樓去幹什麼
Leave that aside for now.
不要說這些了
And you, Hui Ssu?
慧思  你說說
Punish him!
要重罰
May I ask why?
請問三師傅  什麼理由呢
Because that's the only way to satisfy General Wang.
不重罰  王將軍和張指揮的氣難消
Bind Chiu Ming to the Scripture Hall.
把邱明吊在藏經樓上
General, I fear the Abbot
將軍  你這招惡人先告狀
is onto your scheme.
智嚴老住持看穿了
He's a senile old man in his 90s, he won't see through it.
他九十多歲了  糊里糊塗的看不穿
He's not senile in the least.
他一點兒也不糊塗
And Wu Wai is suspicious too.
還有  悟外的話多厲害
It isn't looking good.
這事有點不妙
Only you and Chiu Ming know what happened.
這件事  只有你和邱明知道
He's tied to the Scripture Hall.
他現在綁在藏經樓上
Wait a bit, then go and finish him off.
等會兒你去把他一了百了
Jump!
跳下去
Why are you freeing me?
施主  為什麼放我下來
By order of Esquire Wen -
是文安讓我放你的
he wants to befriend you.
他想跟你結個善緣
Isn't this in defiance of the Abbot's orders?
這樣會不會違背師父的原意
Not at all.
不會
It won't work.
不妥當
Why not?
怎麼
Killing Chiu Ming would be of no avail.
把邱明除了  於事無補啊
A murder while we were here
再說  廟裡出了人命
would reflect badly on us.
有你我在場  傳出去不好聽吶
We came for the scroll,
咱們是為了那個卷子來的
let's not complicate matters.
不能節外生枝
You're right.
也對
Forget it.
那就算了
General, go to the Abbot immediately
將軍  你要立刻到老禪師那裡
and ask him to release Chiu Ming.
替邱明講情  把他放下來
You'll make a good impression.
這樣可以結個善緣
I can't go back on what I said earlier.
我出爾反爾  這怎麼行呢
You can!
行
Your Reverence,
難道讓我說
yesterday my anger blinded me.
老禪師  我昨天是在氣頭上
I didn't think Chiu Ming would be treated so harshly.
沒想到使邱明受這麼重的懲罰
Now I regret it. Can you pardon him?
我有點兒後悔了  你饒了他吧
General, he deserves his punishment.
將軍  他是罪有應得
He's been there for hours.
已經吊了幾個時辰了
Surely he's suffered enough.
也夠他受的了
Can't he be released now?
不如  現在把他放下來吧
It's getting late. Perhaps the General should rest.
時候不早了  將軍也該休息了
We'll discuss this another time.
好好  再說吧
See the General out.
你送送將軍
Yes.
是
Goodnight.
我不打攪了
General...
將軍
Yes?
什麼事
Tomorrow the monks will be tested
從明天起  廟裡的和尚論經證道
and a new abbot will be chosen.
然後推舉新住持
Please be there to advise us.
到時候  想請將軍光臨指導
Certainly.
我一定來
Gentleman, have you studied
他們三個人的答卷
the three disciples' answers?
二位都看過了吧
Yes.
看過了
All excellent.
都很好
General, what do you think?
將軍覺得怎麼樣
Their answers are all very good.
看下來  他們答的都不錯
Approach!
過來
Of all the temple's monks, you three
這幾天看下來  廟裡幾百位弟子
have the best knowledge of Buddhism.
你們三個人論經證道成就最高
Each of you is worthy of the abbot ship.
都能主持本寺的大局
Now His Reverence must make a decision.
現在  請老禪師定奪
The three of you go to the pond behind the temple
你們三個人到廟後邊池塘
and each fetch a bucket of clear water.
每人打一桶清水回來
Will do.
是
Is the water in your buckets clear?
你們的桶裡是清水嗎
Yes!
是
Hui Tung, tell me
慧通  你說說
how you got your clear water?
你這清水是怎麼打的
Only by working with my brothers
弟子和師弟們同心合力
was I able to obtain clear water.
才打到一桶清水
Explain your answer.
你解給我聽
Only when the many streams
就像千溪萬水
have run to the sea
同歸大海
does it reflect the full moon.
才能照出一輪明月
Hui Wen?
慧文  你呢
I filtered the water through fine gauze...
弟子是用細紗濾出來的
for only by ridding oneself of worldly ideas
這就像修持有恆  澄清俗慮
can one rediscover his true nature.
才能返本歸真
Hui Ssu?
慧思
Let nature take its course...
聽其自然
clear heart, clear water.
心清水自清
Hui Ssu!
慧思
Come forward!
你過來
Come, come.
來來來
This is a large temple, with many monks.
自從五祖弘忍之後
Therefore, to avoid internal disputes,
為了怕起爭端  衣缽誤傳
an outsider shall become the new abbot.
本寺因為廟大人多
He shall assume the mantle of leadership.
仍然把架裟交給新住持  作為信物
Chiu Ming!
邱明
Chiu Ming! Come forth!
邱明  你過來
Kneel.
跪下
Henceforth, you shall be called Hui Ming.
從現在起  你法名上慧下明
You shall take my place
接替我主持三寶
in upholding temple traditions
你要承先啟後
and propagating Buddhist doctrine.
傳法度人
Rise!
起來
Now?
現在就來吧
Hui Ming has been chosen as the new abbot.
從現在起  邱明就是本寺的新住持
Respect him as you would the old abbot.
你們要像待師父一樣的待他
Turn!
轉過去
Bow.
拜
Abbot Hui Ming is now in charge.
慧明住持升坐
These are the temple's accounts.
這是萬年冊  本廟契約  帳目
Hui Wen will answer any questions you have.
不明白的地方去問慧文
This is Tripitaka's Mahayana Sutra.
這是玄奘法師的《大乘起信論》殘卷
It has long been a source of trouble here.
這張紙  多年來惹了不少是非
Deal with it properly.
你要妥為處理
Surely.
是
Tomorrow the old Abbot will retire...
師父涅槃的時候要誦彌陀經
to prepare for Nirvana.
明天一早
We will see him off to South Mountain
智嚴禪師在南山已於涅槃
by reciting the Amitabha Sutra.
到時候  頌彌陀經
This is absurd! A convict as abbot!
豈有此理  流犯當住持
It's completely inappropriate!
這成什麼體統
He'll find it's not easy being abbot.
沒那麼容易  不給他點兒顏色看看
He still has me to reckon with!
他也不知道我有多大道行
Gentlemen, please excuse me.
二位  我到前邊兒去看看
Very well.
請便
- I pity him. - Who?
- 也真可憐  - 誰呀
Hui Tung. All his efforts were in vain.
慧通白忙了一場
A monk so power hungry
出家人這麼熱衷權位
isn't fit to be abbot.
就不配當住持
Should I have a talk with the old abbot?
你看我要不要跟智嚴說說
About what?
說什麼呀
To suggest he appoint Hui Tung instead.
請他改派慧通當住持
On what grounds?
什麼理由
As district governor I won't allow
就說  我是地方官
a convict to serve as abbot.
在我治內的廟裡  由一個流犯當住持
I simply won't allow it.
我不能同意
Don't do it!
千萬不要
We have to win Chiu Ming over now.
現在最要緊的是籠絡邱明
How? He hates our guts.
他現在恨你我入骨  怎麼籠絡
I'll see to it.
我去
Over here! Gather around.
過來  大夥兒都過來
Hui Tung has something to say.
大師哥有話跟你們說
Listen...
你們聽我說啊
Huh?
怎麼
Listen to Hui Tung.
聽大師哥講
Speak of this to no one!
你們可千萬別把這事告訴別人
Lead them to the new abbot.
等會兒  你帶頭去見住持
Tell him you're not getting enough to eat
你們就說吃不飽  菜不夠
and you're weak from hunger.
沒油水  手腳發軟
Raise a ruckus. I'll back you up.
撒開了跟他吵  不用怕
Come on! Let's give him hell!
行  給他來個下馬威
Good. I'll leave it to you.
就這麼著了  我先走了
Count on us!
你放心
Is there any other business today?
今天還有什麼事嗎
We captured a smuggler this morning.
早上抓到一個山賊  在前院
Your Reverence.
住持
What is it, Lieutenant?
張指揮  有什麼事嗎
What happened between us earlier
上一次的事兒  實在是出於誤會
was a misunderstanding.
讓住持受了點兒委屈
I'm sorry you suffered for it.
我一直耿耿於懷
I've already forgotten it
那件事  貧僧早就忘了
and I hope you'll forget it too.
施主千萬不要掛在心上
There's something else you should know.
還有件事兒  我不知道應不應該說
Please speak freely, sir.
施主有話儘管說
The food here is...
貴寶寺的伙食  實在太
What?
什麼
The food here in the temple is awful.
貴寶寺的伙食  一向很差
All the monks are complaining.
和尚們都有怨言
I just overheard Hui Tung inciting them
剛才我聽到慧通師傅煽風點火
to confront you about it.
叫大夥兒都跟住持來鬧事
I've come to let you know
我特地來給您送個信
so you won't be taken by surprise.
你心裡要有個底
How can you let us starve?
我們吃不飽怎麼行呢
What does it matter?
這有什麼關係
What if it goes too far?
我們真要這麼辦啊
Don't worry! Hui Tung will back us up!
有大師哥兜著了  怕什麼
Yes!
是呀
What if he doesn't?
那到時候  要是他不認帳呢
We'll leave the monk hood!
最多還俗  不幹了
Easy to say! How would we get by?
你說得倒容易  還俗吃什麼
A bowl of gruel isn't hard to come by.
到哪兒去混兩頓粥還不容易
If you two want to back out,
你們那麼三心兩意的
let's just forget it!
咱們這齣戲  乾脆甭唱了
Your Reverence! We'd like a word with you.
住持  我們有點兒事  想跟您談一談
Very well.
好
Is it about the food?
是不是伙食的事
Yes!
是
You still want to go through with it?
你還要跟著吵啊
Master, you know what we eat.
住持  大伙吃什麼  你也知道
- I do. - Watery gruel,
- 我知道  - 沒菜  沒油水
and little else!
連粥都喝不飽
Monks are falling sick every day!
每月都病倒了好幾個
They're weak and can't see well at night.
手腳發軟  夜裡看不見
Sick? We're starving!
什麼病啊  餓的
Ravaged by hunger!
餓得我氣都發虛
What's going on here?
幹什麼  幹什麼
What's all the shouting about?
你們吵什麼  有什麼好吵的
Quiet?
不要吵了
We'll find a way to improve the food,
伙食的事  咱們想辦法改
but there'll be other changes as well.
可是別的也要改
From now on, monks will not spend
從現在起  這廟裡的和尚
the entire day in contemplation.
不能整天唸經打坐
They'll do farm work as well.
要種莊稼  種菜
Plant crops?
種莊稼
Monks farming? Is he serious?
這和尚種莊稼  我還沒聽說過
Quiet!
別吵
Your Reverence,
住持
I don't think it will work.
叫他們種地  這恐怕行不通吧
Yes, it will.
行得通
We don't know how to farm!
我們不會種莊稼
Then learn.
不會就學
From whom?
跟誰學
I'll teach you.
跟我學
Disperse now.
你們去吧
We need more food!
那伙食還改不改
How can we farm on empty stomachs?
我們吃不飽怎麼行呢
- He's left. - Let's go.
- 人都走了  - 走了
Solving the food problem won't be easy.
住持  這改伙食可不簡單吶
You've seen the temple accounts.
剛才我跟您報過帳了
What we take in barely covers expenses.
咱們廟裡的收入有限  花費有定數
We don't have the money for more food.
這一改伙食  錢就不夠用了
Then go collect alms.
那就去化緣
I'm in charge of alms collection.
化緣的事  本來都是我去辦
Money's scarce this year!
可是年頭不好  化不動啊
Then borrow!
那就去借
Your Reverence!
住持
We've nothing to put up for collateral
那就更難了  再說借要有抵押
unless we go to Esquire Wen.
除非請文居士想辦法
Then go to him now.
好  現在就去
Your Reverence, the food situation...
住持  這改伙食的事
It will be rectified tomorrow.
明天一定改
These are the ones.
就是這幾個
They've been eating meat and drinking wine.
他們偷著喝酒  吃肉
He's their supplier.
每趟都是那個人運進來的
We caught them this morning.
今天早上給抓著了
Where did they get the money?
他們哪兒來的錢
From Hui Wen.
二師哥給的
Brother, what are you saying?
師弟  這是什麼話
They confessed to it.
他們自己招的
I sent them to buy provisions.
我叫他們採辦伙食
I didn't tell them to break their vows!
我沒有叫他們去犯戒
How were such matters handled in the past?
慧通  以前這種事怎麼辦
For monks, three months of solitary confinement.
廟裡的人罰面壁三個月
For laypeople, a severe caning.
外邊兒的人  吊起來打十二板子
I'll take care of it.
這事您交給我好了
Fine. But we'll initiate a new procedure.
好  咱們改個辦法
Monks will go to the rear courtyard
廟裡的人  到後院把井邊那塊地剷平
and clear land to plant vegetables.
種上大白菜
Turn the smuggler over to Lieutenant Chang
那個外邊兒的人  交給張誠
to await trial.
等地方官來發落
- Your Reverence... - Do as I say.
- 住持  - 就這麼辦了
Go now!
你現在就去
- Take care of it immediately! - Yes, sir.
- 你們要立刻辦好  - 是
How dare you defame me?
你怎麼胡說八道的
Your Reverence.
住持
Esquire Wen.
施主
I was on my way to see you.
貧僧正要找你
And I was just on my way to congratulate you
住持  我剛才就想過去給您道賀
but I saw you were very busy.
看見您忙
No congratulations, please.
出家人不講究這些
Esquire...
施主
we want to improve the food here.
廟裡要改善一下伙食
Can you help us?
想請施主幫幫忙
I'd help if I could,
應該的  應該的
but as Hui Wen knows,
不過最近景況實在是緊
I'm having difficulties myself.
二師傅知道的
Well...
那麼
could you help us borrow?
能不能請施主  到外邊兒齋借齋借
Lenders want collateral for loans.
放款的人多數要抵押
We could mortgage the temple property.
那麼就把廟裡的地契押給他們
The lenders wouldn't accept it.
生意人怎麼敢收廟契呢
Why not?
怎麼
If you defaulted, they couldn't sell the temple.
萬一不還錢  他們也不能把廟給賣了
Is there any other way?
還有別的辦法嗎
With the Tripitaka scroll as security,
那部玄奘法師手抄的卷子
you could borrow a large sum.
倒能押不少錢
How much?
能押多少
Tens of thousands of taels of silver.
幾萬兩銀子  大概能押吧
Fine. First give Hui Wen a draft for 10,000 taels.
好  你先寫一萬兩銀票給慧文
As for the scroll,
那部卷子
let me think about it.
我  我想想看
Here are two drafts, each worth 10,000 taels.
這是兩萬兩銀票  一張是你的
One for the temple, one for you.
一張是公款
And here's the key to Scripture Hall.
這是藏經樓的鑰匙
If he changes his mind, resort to your original plan.
萬一他變卦  你再下手
Madame!
如夫人
If they steal it,
現在要能到手
it won't cost me anything.
連一萬兩銀子都省了
Let's go.
走
How can I explain a murder in the temple?
這將來廟裡出了人命怎麼辦呢
Leave it to me!
有我呢
But he's the abbot!
無論如何  他是住持
You go first.
你先去
Understand?
這你該明白了吧
On my own I'm no match for him.
指揮  我怕一個人弄不過他
Don't worry. I've got your back.
別怕  有我給你打接應
Go on! Go!
去吧  去去去去
Your Reverence!
住持
Madame.
施主
Your Reverence!
住持
Hui Tung and Chang Cheng are plotting to kill you!
慧通  張誠要害你  留神點兒
Madame...
施主
Madame!
Put some salve on it and you'll be fine.
你不用怕  馬上找點兒刀創藥擦上
Then go watch over the Scripture Hall tonight.
然後睡在藏經樓門口
If there's any trouble there,
今天晚上  藏經樓要是出了什麼事
I'll hold you responsible.
明天唯你是問
Now go!
去吧
Have you seen Chang Cheng?
有沒有看見張誠
Go out the back. Meet me at the riverside.
走後門  河邊兒見
See you there!
河邊兒見
- General. - Esquire Wen.
- 將軍  - 文兄啊
I...
我
Well, this has been an eventful visit.
我們這一趟總算是功德圓滿了
Indeed it has.
是呀  是呀
Are you leaving today too, General?
將軍也是今天下山嗎
Yes.
馬上就走
I've official duties to attend to.
衙門裡還有很多事情啊
Then I won't delay you further.
那我就不另外辭行了
You're too polite!
不要客氣  不要客氣
- Goodbye. - Goodbye.
- 再見  - 再見  再見
- After you. - Please.
- 請  - 請
Chang Cheng!
張誠
"White Fox has scroll. In pursuit.
狐盜捲逃  直追
Await you at riverside."
河邊候駕
Damn it!
河邊
Where by the riverside?
也不寫明河邊在哪裡
Hurry!
走
Run!
快跑
走
- What about Gold Lock? - Run!
- 金鎖呢  - 走
Chang Cheng.
張誠
Isn't this Gold Lock?
這不是金鎖嗎
After them!
搜
Come on!
走
Hurry!
I say, sir, can you ferry us across?
老大爺  您渡我們過江好吧
I'll pay you 10 taels of silver.
我給您十兩銀子
20, then!
好  二十兩
All right?
好吧
Let's go!
走吧
Hurry!
快點兒開船
Wait!
等一等
- What? - You haven't paid him.
- 幹嘛  - 還沒給他錢呢
On second thought...
不對
What if he betrays us?
這老頭一會兒告訴他們就糟了
Better yet...
不如
That won't do!
這不大好吧
Old fellow, I forgot to pay you.
老大爺  還沒給您錢呢
Old fellow, over here, over here!
老大爺  您過來  過來呀
Please, sir... stop!
二位施主  請留步
Esquire Wen.
施主
Brother Hui Wen.
慧文師傅
Esquire Wen.
文施主
I've told the Abbot all about our plot.
我跟你的事  我都對住持說了
You stole and murdered on temple grounds.
現在你在廟裡偷了東西  又殺了人
How will you account for that?
這怎麼了結呢
Chang Cheng attacked me!
是張誠先動的手啊
But you've no proof of it!
那是死無對證啊
Chang Cheng was a known killer.
張誠是有名的酷吏
The brute got what he deserved.
他一向作惡多端  死有餘辜啊
That may indeed be so,
這在情理上也許說得過去
but the law won't see it that way!
在國法上可講不通啊
Then... what can I do?
那  那到這個地步  我
Return with me and beg for the Abbot's mercy.
文施主  你還是跟我回去  求求住持
Perhaps he'll be lenient.
也許能夠從輕發落
So... all my efforts were in vain?
那  那這趟我不是白來了
I'm afraid so.
我看是白來了
Go to hell!
哎呀
Esquire Wen!
文施主
Esquire! Not that way...!
文施主  那兒不能去啊
This tattered parchment
這張爛紙
has caused trouble for far too long.
多少年來是本寺禍亂之源
Now I'm returning it to Tripitaka.
現在  我把它還給玄奘法師
General Wang.
王將軍
The Mahayana Sutra's true value is in its meaning.
《大乘起信論》可貴之處  在它的文意
It should be available to all.
它應該廣為傳播
I've made scores of copies.
師父早已經印好了幾十份
One of them for you, General.
現在  送給將軍一份
Call her over to take the tonsure.
叫她過來  給她剃度
Come.
你過來
Kneel!
跪下
Chant the sutra.
誦經
THE END
劇 終